For loops iterate over every element in a sequence,
and while loops iterate until they're stopping condition is met.
This is sufficient for most purposes but we
sometimes need more precise control over when a loop should end.
In these cases, we use the break keyword.
A loop will terminate immediately if it encounters a break statement.
We can use this to end the loop if we detect that some condition has been met.
The break keyword can be used in both for and while loops.
For example, suppose you want to load a cargo ship with a list of items called manifest.
This list contains tuples of items and their weights.
Ideally, you would like to load all the items on
the ship but the ship has a maximum weight capacity.
Therefore, when the ship's capacity is reached,
you want to stop loading.
To accomplish this, let's use a for loop loading
each item and keeping track of the weight of all the items we have loaded so far.
Here, we check if the ship's total cargo weight reaches
its maximum capacity of 100 with each addition of cargo.
If it does, we use a break statement to stop loading.
If not, we load the next item and add on its weight.
Here's what we end up loading.
That's not good.
The boat is severely over its weight limit of 100.
The break statement did prevent us from putting every item on
the boat but we still exceeded the limit by 111.
It's difficult to see what's gone wrong.
One strategy we can use is to add print statements in the code.
This is a really handy technique as it can give us some insight
into what happens in the code as it's running step-by-step.
Having print statements frequently that give context can
really assist us in understanding what went wrong here.
Here's the loop with debugging statements added.
Debugging is the process of identifying and removing errors in your code.
Here, we can see that we didn't break until the weight exceeded 100,
when really, we should break before that item is added.
Additionally, we can see that the cheeses still could
have fit if the machine wasn't added.
This brings us to another statement.
Sometimes, rather than breaking out of the loop completely,
there will be times we want to skip simply one iteration of the loop.
In this case, we would use the continue keyword.
In this example, we iterate through a list of
foods and increment account if the food is a fruit.
Here, we terminate an iteration if the food is not found in fruit.
Otherwise, we add one to fruit count.
So when food is hummus or toast in this loop,
the rest of the loop is completely skipped.